Captioning funded by CBS
and FORD--
BUILT FOR THE ROAD AHEAD.
>> Logan: ON THE TENTH
ANNIVERSARY OF THE ATTACKS ON
9/11, WE BRING YOU THE STORY OF
THE FBI AGENT WHO HELPED TO
CRACK THE CASE AGAINST AL QAEDA.
>> THE MOST IMPORTANT
INFORMATION IS IDENTIFYING
KHALID SHEIK MOHAMMED AS THE
MASTERMIND OF 9/11.
>> Logan: ALI SOUFAN HAS NEVER
SHOWN HIS FACE ON TV, BUT
TONIGHT, HE TELLS "60 MINUTES"
ABOUT INTERROGATING AND
OUTWITTING SOME OF BIN LADEN'S
LIEUTENANTS.
>> AND I SAID, "WELL, I KNOW
THAT AL QAEDA DID THAT.
SOMEONE TOLD ME."
HE SAID, "WHO TOLD YOU?"
I SAID, "YOU DID."
HE TOTALLY COLLAPSED.
>> Logan: HE COLLAPSED?
>> HE PUT HIS HANDS LIKE THIS ON
HIS FACE AND WENT DOWN.
AND HE STARTS SHAKING.
HE KNEW WHAT HE DID.
>> Logan: HE KNEW THAT HE...
>> HE JUST GAVE UP BIN LADEN, HE
JUST GAVE UP AL QAEDA ON 9/11.
>> HE COMES IN, HIS HANDS ARE
CUPPED.
AND HE'S GOT BONES IN HIS HANDS.
AND HE GOES UP TO THE MEDICAL
EXAMINER AND HE PUTS THE BONES
IN FRONT OF HIM AND HE GOES,
"THIS IS MY SON."
>> Pelley: IT WAS AFTER HEARING
STORY AFTER STORY LIKE THIS THAT
DR. BENJAMIN LUFT DECIDED TO
COMPILE THE WORLD TRADE CENTER
ORAL HISTORY PROJECT-- UNEDITED,
UNVARNISHED REALITY AS
EXPERIENCED BY THE RESPONDERS TO
GROUND ZERO.
>> IT WAS CRAZY.
>> IT WAS ALMOST LIKE TAKING A
CIVICS CLASS AS TO WHAT IS
IMPORTANT ABOUT BEING A CITIZEN.
WHAT IS IMPORTANT ABOUT BEING A
HUMAN BEING.
WHAT IS IMPORTANT TO BEING AN
AMERICAN.
>> I'M STEVE KROFT.
>> I'M LESLEY STAHL.
>> I'M BOB SIMON.
>> I'M MORLEY SAFER.
>> I'M LARA LOGAN.
>> I'M SCOTT PELLEY.
THOSE STORIES TONIGHT ON THIS
SPECIAL 9/11 EDITION OF "60
MINUTES."
>> Logan: TONIGHT, ON THE TENTH
ANNIVERSARY OF 9/11, WE BRING
YOU THE STORY OF SOMEONE WHO HAS
NEVER SHOWN HIS FACE ON
TELEVISION BEFORE, AND FOR GOOD
REASON.
ALI SOUFAN WAS ONE OF THE FBI'S
SECRET WEAPONS IN ITS FIGHT
AGAINST AL QAEDA.
A LEBANESE-AMERICAN, FLUENT IN
ARABIC, HE INTERROGATED AL QAEDA
PRISONERS AT SECRET LOCATIONS
ALL OVER THE WORLD.
SOUFAN WAS KNOWN FOR HIS ABILITY
TO OUTWIT TERRORISTS.
AND HE'S TELLING HIS STORY IN A
NEW BOOK, "THE BLACK BANNERS,"
PARTS OF WHICH HAVE BEEN BLACKED
OUT BECAUSE THE CIA SAYS THEY
CONTAIN CLASSIFIED INFORMATION.
ON THE DAY OF THE SEPTEMBER 11
ATTACKS, ALI SOUFAN WAS
THOUSANDS OF MILES AWAY FROM
GROUND ZERO, BUT IN A UNIQUE
POSITION TO HELP FIND THOSE
RESPONSIBLE.
WHAT WAS YOUR FIRST THOUGHT?
>> Ali Soufan: IT WAS AL QAEDA.
ABSOLUTELY, I HAD NO DOUBT IN MY
MIND.
I HAD NO DOUBT IN MY MIND.
TWO PLANES AT THE SAME TIME,
HITTING THE WORLD TRADE CENTER.
>> Logan: ON 9/11, FBI AGENT ALI
SOUFAN WAS IN YEMEN, WHERE HIS
NEW YORK-BASED TEAM HAD BEEN
INVESTIGATING THE DEADLY AL
QAEDA ATTACK A YEAR EARLIER ON
THE U.S.S. "COLE."
SOUFAN AND HIS TEAM WERE
PREPARING TO FLY BACK TO NEW
YORK WHEN FBI HEADQUARTERS
ORDERED HIM AND HIS PARTNER TO
STAY PUT.
AND AT THIS POINT, EVERY FIBER
OF YOUR BEING IS SCREAMING,
"I'VE GOT TO GET BACK TO NEW
YORK"?
>> Soufan: THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT I
SAID.
I SAID, YOU KNOW, "NEW YORK IS
UNDER ATTACK, AMERICA UNDER
ATTACK.
WE CAN INVESTIGATE THE "COLE"
SOME OTHER TIME."
AND THE ANSWER WAS, "NO, ALI,
IT'S NOT ABOUT THE "COLE."
IT'S... IT'S ACTUALLY ABOUT WHAT
HAPPENED HERE."
AND I WAS FEELING LIKE A KNIFE
GONE IN MY HEART.
I... I FELT, "WHAT DID WE MISS?
WHAT DID WE MISS?"
>> Logan: SOUFAN WONDERED
WHETHER HE AND HIS TEAM HAD
MISSED SOME HINT OF THE 9/11
PLOT AS THEY INVESTIGATED THE
EARLIER ATTACK ON THE "COLE,"
AND HIS MISSION IN YEMEN NOW
TOOK ON A NEW URGENCY.
THERE WERE ALREADY A NUMBER OF
AL QAEDA OPERATIVES IN CUSTODY
IN YEMEN, AND FOR THE FBI, ALI
SOUFAN WAS THE RIGHT MAN TO
QUESTION THEM ABOUT 9/11.
HE HAD BEEN INVESTIGATING AL
QAEDA FOR FOUR YEARS, AND KNEW A
LOT ABOUT ITS OPERATIVES AND ITS
IDEOLOGY.
HE WAS FLUENT IN ARABIC, A
MUSLIM HIMSELF, AND AT 30 YEARS
OLD, STARTING TO MAKE A NAME FOR
HIMSELF AS ONE OF THE BUREAU'S
BEST INTERROGATORS OF ISLAMIC
EXTREMISTS.
WHAT MAKES A GOOD INTERVIEWER OR
INTERROGATOR?
>> Soufan: KNOWLEDGE AND
EMPATHY.
I THINK THESE ARE THE TWO
THINGS.
YOU NEED TO CONNECT WITH PEOPLE
ON A HUMAN LEVEL, REGARDLESS IF
THEY DON'T LIKE YOU, IF THEY
WANT TO KILL YOU.
>> Logan: IS IT HARD TO HAVE
EMPATHY WITH SOMEONE WHO'S JUST
KILLED, OR HELPED TO KILL,
THOUSANDS OF AMERICANS?
>> Soufan: OH, ABSOLUTELY.
I WAS WITH ONE GUY WHO'S TELLING
ME HE WANT TO SLAUGHTER ME LIKE
A SHEEP.
>> Logan: WHAT DID YOU SAY TO
HIM?
>> Soufan: I KIND OF, LIKE,
POLITELY PUT HIM IN HIS PLACE.
>> Logan: I WOULD LIKE TO
UNDERSTAND WHAT "POLITELY PUT
HIM IN HIS PLACE" MEANS.
>> Soufan: WE HAD A FRUIT NEXT
TO US AND THERE'S A KNIFE TO CUT
THE FRUIT.
I GAVE HIM THE KNIFE.
I SAID, "GO AHEAD AND DO IT
NOW."
HE LOOKED AT ME.
I SAID, "I THOUGHT SO.
SO SIT DOWN AND SHUT YOUR MOUTH
AND LET'S TALK."
>> Logan: ARE THEY TRYING TO
TURN THE SITUATION AROUND?
ARE THEY TRYING TO TURN IT ON
YOU?
>> Soufan: WELL, YOU KNOW WHAT?
THERE IS SOMETHING THAT THEY
DON'T EXPECT WHEN THEY ARE...
THEY ARE BEING INTERROGATED BY
AMERICANS.
THEY DON'T EXPECT A PERSON COMES
WITH THEM.
THEY HAVE, LIKE, TEA, THEY HAVE
COFFEE-- SIT DOWN, TALK, TRYING
TO KNOW EACH OTHER, TRYING TO
BUILD A RAPPORT.
AND THAT SCARES THEM, THAT
SHAKES THEM.
BECAUSE THEY WERE TRAINED THAT
WE ARE SO EVIL, AND WE TORTURE
AND WE KILL.
AND THAT IS THE REASON OF THE
RAGE AGAINST US.
SO THEY TELL YOU A LOT OF STUFF
TO PISS YOU OFF, AND THEN THEY
CAN SAY, "SEE?
HE IS EVIL."
SO IN MY CASE, I TRY TO DEPRIVE
THEM FROM THAT.
>> Logan: DO YOU THINK THE FACT
THAT YOU WERE A MUSLIM GAVE YOU
AN ADVANTAGE IN SOME CASES AND
IN SOME WAYS?
>> Soufan: NO.
BUT THE FACT THAT MAYBE I
UNDERSTOOD THE CULTURE, THE FACT
THAT I GENUINELY, AS A PERSON,
HAVE AN INTEREST IN THESE KIND
OF THINGS, THAT PROBABLY HELPED
ME.
>> Logan: THERE HAS BEEN TIMES
WHERE YOU'VE GOT INTO REALLY
DEEP, RELIGIOUS...
>> Soufan: RIGHT.
>> Logan: ...ARGUMENTS WITH SOME
PRETTY HIGH-LEVEL BAD GUYS.
>> Soufan: WELL, IT HAPPENED
FREQUENTLY, YEAH.
>> Logan: DID YOU WIN THOSE
ARGUMENTS?
>> Soufan: WELL, I DON'T KNOW IF
I CONVINCED THEM.
BUT I KNOW, TOWARDS THE END, I
HAVE MY CONFESSION AND THAT
WHAT'S I CARE ABOUT.
( LAUGHTER )
>> Logan: JUST ONE WEEK AFTER
9/11, SOUFAN AND HIS PARTNER
FOUND THEMSELVES FACE TO FACE
WITH OSAMA BIN LADEN'S
BODYGUARD, ABU JANDAL.
HE'D BEEN CAUGHT AND IMPRISONED
IN YEMEN NEARLY SEVEN MONTHS
BEFORE 9/11, BUT NOW THAT BIN
LADEN HAD ATTACKED ON U.S. SOIL,
IT WAS IMPORTANT TO SEE IF ABU
JANDAL COULD HELP THE FBI BUILD
A CASE AGAINST THOSE
RESPONSIBLE.
>> Soufan: HE WALKED, SAT IN HIS
CHAIR, AND LITERALLY MOVED THE
CHAIR TOWARDS THE TWO YEMENI
INTERROGATORS THAT'S THERE.
AND HE SAID, "I DON'T
ACKNOWLEDGE THEM.
I DON'T ACKNOWLEDGE THEIR
EXISTENCE."
>> Logan: AND WHY IS HE DOING
THAT?
>> Soufan: HE HATE US.
HE HATE AMERICANS.
>> Logan: SO HOW DID YOU GET HIM
TO OPEN UP?
>> Soufan: WELL, IT WAS A
PROCESS.
WE WERE ABLE TO BUILD A RAPPORT
WITH HIM.
AND HE TALKED A LOT ABOUT, YOU
KNOW, REVOLUTIONS AND THE
HISTORY OF REVOLUTIONS.
SO I START TELLING HIM ABOUT THE
AMERICAN REVOLUTION, TOO.
AND WE GOT HIM A BOOK IN ARABIC
ABOUT GEORGE WASHINGTON AND THE
AMERICAN REVOLUTION THAT HE
ACTUALLY STAYED ALL NIGHT
READING.
HE WAS FASCINATED BY IT.
BUT HE'S PRACTICING TYPICAL
COUNTER-INTERROGATION
TECHNIQUES, WHERE HE GIVES YOU
WHAT HE THINKS YOU KNOW SO YOU
WILL THINK HE'S COOPERATING.
>> Logan: SOUFAN SAYS WHEN ABU
JANDAL LOOKED AT A BOOK OF
PHOTOS OF KNOWN AL QAEDA
MEMBERS, HE IDENTIFIED VERY FEW
AND KEPT PASSING OVER THE PHOTO
OF THIS MAN, MARWAN AL SHEHHI,
ONE OF THE 9/11 HIJACKERS.
SOUFAN KNEW ABU JANDAL HAD CARED
FOR EL SHEHHI YEARS AGO WHEN HE
WAS VERY SICK.
SO THE FACT THAT HE WAS NOT
IDENTIFYING HIM IMMEDIATELY WAS
A SIGNAL TO YOU THAT HE WAS NOT
BEING HONEST?
>> Soufan: EXACTLY.
SO I SAID TO HIM, "SO YOU WANT
TO TELL ME YOU DON'T KNOW THIS
GUY?
KANDAHAR, DECEMBER 1999,
RAMADAN.
HE GOT VERY SICK.
YOU WERE NURSING HIM AND PUTTING
SOUP ON HIS LIPS, SO HE WON'T
GET DEHYDRATED."
I TOOK THE BOOK.
I SAID, "LET ME MAKE IT VERY
CLEAR TO YOU.
YOU DON'T KNOW HOW MANY PEOPLE
IN THE BOOK WORKS FOR ME.
IN THE BOOK WE CAUGHT AND
YOU DON'T KNOW HOW MANY PEOPLE
THEY'RE COOPERATING.
IN THE BOOK WE CAUGHT AND
AND THAT IS THE CARD THAT I HAVE
THEY'RE COOPERATING.
TO KNOW IF YOU'RE COOPERATING OR
AND THAT IS THE CARD THAT I HAVE
NOT.
TO KNOW IF YOU'RE COOPERATING OR
WHY DON'T YOU LOOK AT THE BOOK
NOT.
AGAIN?"
WHY DON'T YOU LOOK AT THE BOOK
HE IDENTIFIED ALMOST EVERYONE IN
AGAIN?"
THE BOOK.
HE IDENTIFIED ALMOST EVERYONE IN
>> Logan: AMONG THOSE ABU JANDAL
THE BOOK.
IDENTIFIED AS AL QAEDA MEMBERS
>> Logan: AMONG THOSE ABU JANDAL
WERE SEVEN OF THE TERRORISTS WHO
IDENTIFIED AS AL QAEDA MEMBERS
FLEW PLANES INTO THE WORLD TRADE
WERE SEVEN OF THE TERRORISTS WHO
CENTER AND THE PENTAGON.
FLEW PLANES INTO THE WORLD TRADE
ABU JANDAL DIDN'T KNOW THEY HAD
CENTER AND THE PENTAGON.
BEEN INVOLVED IN THE 9/11 PLOT
ABU JANDAL DIDN'T KNOW THEY HAD
BECAUSE HE'D BEEN IN PRISON, AND
BEEN INVOLVED IN THE 9/11 PLOT
HE INSISTED THAT AL QAEDA WAS
BECAUSE HE'D BEEN IN PRISON, AND
NOT BEHIND THE ATTACK.
HE INSISTED THAT AL QAEDA WAS
HE DIDN'T BELIEVE IT?
NOT BEHIND THE ATTACK.
>> Soufan: HE WAS VERY ADAMANT
HE DIDN'T BELIEVE IT?
THAT BIN LADEN DIDN'T DO IT.
>> Soufan: HE WAS VERY ADAMANT
>> Logan: SO WHAT HAPPENS THEN?
THAT BIN LADEN DIDN'T DO IT.
>> Soufan: I SAID, "WELL, I KNOW
>> Logan: SO WHAT HAPPENS THEN?
THAT AL QAEDA DID THAT.
>> Soufan: I SAID, "WELL, I KNOW
SOMEONE TOLD ME."
THAT AL QAEDA DID THAT.
HE SAID, "WHO TOLD YOU?"
SOMEONE TOLD ME."
I SAID, "YOU DID."
HE SAID, "WHO TOLD YOU?"
AND HE GETS SO MAD.
I SAID, "YOU DID."
"YOU'RE PUTTING WORDS IN MY
AND HE GETS SO MAD.
MOUTH.
"YOU'RE PUTTING WORDS IN MY
I NEVER SAID AL QAEDA DID THAT."
MOUTH.
I SAID, "DO YOU KNOW WHO FLEW
I NEVER SAID AL QAEDA DID THAT."
THE PLANES INTO THE WORLD TRADE
I SAID, "DO YOU KNOW WHO FLEW
CENTER AND THE PENTAGON?"
THE PLANES INTO THE WORLD TRADE
AND I TOOK THE SEVEN PHOTOS THAT
CENTER AND THE PENTAGON?"
HE IDENTIFIED AND PUT IT IN
AND I TOOK THE SEVEN PHOTOS THAT
FRONT OF HIM.
HE IDENTIFIED AND PUT IT IN
I SAID, "THOSE, MY FRIEND, ARE
FRONT OF HIM.
NOT MY SOURCES; THOSE ARE THE
I SAID, "THOSE, MY FRIEND, ARE
PEOPLE WHO FLEW THE PLANES."
NOT MY SOURCES; THOSE ARE THE
HE TOTALLY COLLAPSED.
PEOPLE WHO FLEW THE PLANES."
>> Logan: HE COLLAPSED?
HE TOTALLY COLLAPSED.
>> Soufan: HE PUT HIS HANDS LIKE
>> Logan: HE COLLAPSED?
THIS ON HIS FACE AND WENT DOWN.
>> Soufan: HE PUT HIS HANDS LIKE
AND HE STARTS SHAKING.
THIS ON HIS FACE AND WENT DOWN.
HE KNEW WHAT HE DID.
AND HE STARTS SHAKING.
>> Logan: HE KNEW THAT HE...
HE KNEW WHAT HE DID.
>> Soufan: HE JUST GAVE UP BIN
>> Logan: HE KNEW THAT HE...
LADEN, HE JUST GAVE UP AL QAEDA
>> Soufan: HE JUST GAVE UP BIN
ON 9/11.
LADEN, HE JUST GAVE UP AL QAEDA
AND AFTER THAT, THE LEVEL OF
ON 9/11.
COOPERATION WAS VERY DIFFERENT.
AND AFTER THAT, THE LEVEL OF
WE ENDED UP SPENDING DAYS AND
COOPERATION WAS VERY DIFFERENT.
DAYS WITH HIM.
WE ENDED UP SPENDING DAYS AND
>> Logan: ABU JANDAL PROVIDED
DAYS WITH HIM.
NEARLY 100 PAGES OF INFORMATION,
>> Logan: ABU JANDAL PROVIDED
ACCORDING TO SOUFAN'S FBI
NEARLY 100 PAGES OF INFORMATION,
REPORT, INCLUDING INTRICATE
ACCORDING TO SOUFAN'S FBI
DETAILS ABOUT AL QAEDA'S
REPORT, INCLUDING INTRICATE
"TRAINING FACILITIES,"
DETAILS ABOUT AL QAEDA'S
"COMMUNICATIONS" AND "WEAPONRY."
"TRAINING FACILITIES,"
IT WAS QUITE AN ACHIEVEMENT FOR
"COMMUNICATIONS" AND "WEAPONRY."
SOMEONE WHO MIGHT BEST BE
IT WAS QUITE AN ACHIEVEMENT FOR
DESCRIBED AS AN ACCIDENTAL FBI
SOMEONE WHO MIGHT BEST BE
AGENT.
DESCRIBED AS AN ACCIDENTAL FBI
SOUFAN GREW UP IN LEBANON DURING
AGENT.
THAT COUNTRY'S BRUTAL CIVIL WAR,
SOUFAN GREW UP IN LEBANON DURING
AND HE MOVED WITH HIS FAMILY TO
THAT COUNTRY'S BRUTAL CIVIL WAR,
THE U.S. WHEN HE WAS 17.
AND HE MOVED WITH HIS FAMILY TO
HE WAS A FRAT BOY AT MANSFIELD
THE U.S. WHEN HE WAS 17.
UNIVERSITY IN PENNSYLVANIA,
HE WAS A FRAT BOY AT MANSFIELD
PLANNING A CAREER IN ACADEMIA,
UNIVERSITY IN PENNSYLVANIA,
WHEN A COLLEGE ADMINISTRATOR
PLANNING A CAREER IN ACADEMIA,
SUGGESTED HE APPLY FOR A JOB
WHEN A COLLEGE ADMINISTRATOR
WITH THE FBI.
SUGGESTED HE APPLY FOR A JOB
>> Soufan: WHEN HE SAID THAT, I
WITH THE FBI.
WAS LIKE... AS IF HE WAS TELLING
>> Soufan: WHEN HE SAID THAT, I
ME, "YOU'RE GOING TO BE, LIKE,
WAS LIKE... AS IF HE WAS TELLING
IN THE CIRCUS, OR YOU'RE GOING
ME, "YOU'RE GOING TO BE, LIKE,
TO BE, YOU KNOW, A RACECAR
IN THE CIRCUS, OR YOU'RE GOING
DRIVER."
TO BE, YOU KNOW, A RACECAR
I MEAN, "FBI?
DRIVER."
WHAT ARE YOU TALKING ABOUT," YOU
I MEAN, "FBI?
KNOW?
WHAT ARE YOU TALKING ABOUT," YOU
PEOPLE WERE LAUGHING.
KNOW?
MY FRIENDS...
PEOPLE WERE LAUGHING.
>> Logan: YOUR FRAT BROTHERS.
MY FRIENDS...
>> Soufan: YEAH, WERE LAUGHING.
>> Logan: YOUR FRAT BROTHERS.
I'M LIKE, "THEY WILL SEND YOU
>> Soufan: YEAH, WERE LAUGHING.
BACK THE APPLICATION."
I'M LIKE, "THEY WILL SEND YOU
>> Logan: A LITTLE BIT OF A
BACK THE APPLICATION."
CHALLENGE.
>> Logan: A LITTLE BIT OF A
>> Soufan: I WAS LIKE, "OKAY.
CHALLENGE.
WE'LL SEE ABOUT THAT."
>> Soufan: I WAS LIKE, "OKAY.
>> Logan: IN 1997, AFTER GETTING
WE'LL SEE ABOUT THAT."
A MASTER'S DEGREE IN
>> Logan: IN 1997, AFTER GETTING
INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS, HE
A MASTER'S DEGREE IN
JOINED THE FBI'S NEW YORK OFFICE
INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS, HE
AS A ROOKIE COUNTER-TERRORISM
JOINED THE FBI'S NEW YORK OFFICE
AGENT, AND HE WAS LITTLE MORE
AS A ROOKIE COUNTER-TERRORISM
THAN THREE YEARS ON THE JOB WHEN
AGENT, AND HE WAS LITTLE MORE
HE WAS MADE THE CASE AGENT FOR
THAN THREE YEARS ON THE JOB WHEN
THE FBI'S INVESTIGATION OF THE
HE WAS MADE THE CASE AGENT FOR
ATTACK ON THE U.S.S. "COLE."
THE FBI'S INVESTIGATION OF THE
IN MARCH 2002, THE U.S. CAPTURED
ATTACK ON THE U.S.S. "COLE."
ITS FIRST HIGH-VALUE TERRORIST
IN MARCH 2002, THE U.S. CAPTURED
OPERATIVE, ABU ZUBAYDAH, AFTER A
ITS FIRST HIGH-VALUE TERRORIST
FIRE-FIGHT IN PAKISTAN.
OPERATIVE, ABU ZUBAYDAH, AFTER A
ALI SOUFAN AND HIS PARTNER WERE
FIRE-FIGHT IN PAKISTAN.
CALLED IN TO ASSIST IN THE CIA
ALI SOUFAN AND HIS PARTNER WERE
INTERROGATION AT A SECRET
CALLED IN TO ASSIST IN THE CIA
LOCATION IN THAILAND.
INTERROGATION AT A SECRET
ABU ZUBAYDAH WAS SEVERELY
LOCATION IN THAILAND.
WOUNDED BUT STILL ABLE TO
ABU ZUBAYDAH WAS SEVERELY
COMMUNICATE.
WOUNDED BUT STILL ABLE TO
FROM U.S. INTELLIGENCE FILES,
COMMUNICATE.
SOUFAN HAD LEARNED A LOT ABOUT
FROM U.S. INTELLIGENCE FILES,
ABU ZUBAYDAH, AND HE TOLD US HE
SOUFAN HAD LEARNED A LOT ABOUT
PUT THAT KNOWLEDGE TO GOOD USE
ABU ZUBAYDAH, AND HE TOLD US HE
RIGHT WAY.
PUT THAT KNOWLEDGE TO GOOD USE
>> Soufan: WHEN I FIRST MET HIM,
RIGHT WAY.
I ASKED HIM HIS NAME, AND HE
>> Soufan: WHEN I FIRST MET HIM,
GAVE ME A FAKE NAME.
I ASKED HIM HIS NAME, AND HE
>> Logan: "DAWUD."
GAVE ME A FAKE NAME.
>> Soufan: A DIFFERENT NAME--
>> Logan: "DAWUD."
"DAWUD."
>> Soufan: A DIFFERENT NAME--
AND I SAID TO HIM, "WHAT IF I
"DAWUD."
CALL YOU 'HANI'?"
AND I SAID TO HIM, "WHAT IF I
AND THE LOOK ON HIS FACE WAS
CALL YOU 'HANI'?"
LIKE...
AND THE LOOK ON HIS FACE WAS
YOU KNOW?
LIKE...
LIKE... YOU KNOW, LIKE, YOU
YOU KNOW?
KNOW, "THAT'S IT.
LIKE... YOU KNOW, LIKE, YOU
IT'S OVER."
KNOW, "THAT'S IT.
AND HE JUST LOOKED AT ME AND
IT'S OVER."
HE... JUST SHOOK HIS HEAD.
AND HE JUST LOOKED AT ME AND
HE WAS SHOCKED.
HE... JUST SHOOK HIS HEAD.
"HANI" IS THE NAME THAT HIS
HE WAS SHOCKED.
MOTHER CALLED HIM AS A CHILD.
"HANI" IS THE NAME THAT HIS
SO HE KNEW THAT I KNOW
MOTHER CALLED HIM AS A CHILD.
EVERYTHING ABOUT HIM.
SO HE KNEW THAT I KNOW
>> Logan: WHY DO YOU THINK THAT
EVERYTHING ABOUT HIM.
MATTERED SO MUCH?
>> Logan: WHY DO YOU THINK THAT
>> Soufan: IT KIND OF TOLD HIM
MATTERED SO MUCH?
THAT YOU CANNOT PLAY GAMES WITH
>> Soufan: IT KIND OF TOLD HIM
US.
THAT YOU CANNOT PLAY GAMES WITH
WE KNOW WHO YOU ARE.
US.
>> Logan: AND WHAT DO YOU THINK
WE KNOW WHO YOU ARE.
IS THE MOST IMPORTANT
>> Logan: AND WHAT DO YOU THINK
INFORMATION THAT CAME OUT OF
IS THE MOST IMPORTANT
THAT?
INFORMATION THAT CAME OUT OF
>> Soufan: THE MOST IMPORTANT
THAT?
INFORMATION IS IDENTIFYING
>> Soufan: THE MOST IMPORTANT
KHALID SHEIKH MOHAMMED AS A
INFORMATION IS IDENTIFYING
MASTERMIND OF 9/11.
KHALID SHEIKH MOHAMMED AS A
>> Logan: AT THE TIME, KHALID
MASTERMIND OF 9/11.
SHEIKH MOHAMMED, OR "KSM", WAS
>> Logan: AT THE TIME, KHALID
ON THE FBI'S MOST WANTED LIST
SHEIKH MOHAMMED, OR "KSM", WAS
FOR OTHER TERRORIST PLOTS.
ON THE FBI'S MOST WANTED LIST
U.S. INTELLIGENCE SUSPECTED HE
FOR OTHER TERRORIST PLOTS.
WAS INVOLVED IN 9/11, BUT THE
U.S. INTELLIGENCE SUSPECTED HE
FBI DIDN'T HAVE ANY EVIDENCE OF
WAS INVOLVED IN 9/11, BUT THE
THAT.
FBI DIDN'T HAVE ANY EVIDENCE OF
ALI SOUFAN AND HIS PARTNER,
THAT.
STEVE GAUDIN, MEANT TO SHOW ABU
ALI SOUFAN AND HIS PARTNER,
ZUBAYDAH A PHOTO OF SOMEONE ELSE
STEVE GAUDIN, MEANT TO SHOW ABU
ON THE MOST WANTED LIST, BUT
ZUBAYDAH A PHOTO OF SOMEONE ELSE
THEY SHOWED ABU ZUBAYDAH THIS
ON THE MOST WANTED LIST, BUT
PHOTO OF K.S.M. BY MISTAKE.
THEY SHOWED ABU ZUBAYDAH THIS
>> Soufan: HE LOOKS AT ME AND HE
PHOTO OF K.S.M. BY MISTAKE.
SAYS, "DON'T PLAY GAMES WITH ME,
>> Soufan: HE LOOKS AT ME AND HE
BROTHER.
SAYS, "DON'T PLAY GAMES WITH ME,
DON'T PLAY GAMES WITH ME.
BROTHER.
YOU KNOW WHO THIS GUY.
DON'T PLAY GAMES WITH ME.
THIS IS... THIS IS MUKHTAR.
YOU KNOW WHO THIS GUY.
THIS IS MASTERMIND OF THE PLANE
THIS IS... THIS IS MUKHTAR.
OPERATIONS."
THIS IS MASTERMIND OF THE PLANE
>> Logan: OF 9/11?
OPERATIONS."
>> Soufan: THAT'S WHAT AL QAEDA
>> Logan: OF 9/11?
CALL 9/11, "THE PLANE
>> Soufan: THAT'S WHAT AL QAEDA
OPERATIONS."
CALL 9/11, "THE PLANE
>> Logan: MUKHTAR?
OPERATIONS."
THAT'S...
>> Logan: MUKHTAR?
>> Soufan: MUKHTAR.
THAT'S...
>> Logan: ...THE NAME HE USES?
>> Soufan: MUKHTAR.
>> Soufan: THAT WAS THE ALIAS
>> Logan: ...THE NAME HE USES?
FOR KSM.
>> Soufan: THAT WAS THE ALIAS
>> Logan: DID YOU KNOW THAT?
FOR KSM.
>> Soufan: NO.
>> Logan: DID YOU KNOW THAT?
I HAD NO IDEA.
>> Soufan: NO.
THE ONLY THING I KNEW AT THE
I HAD NO IDEA.
TIME, I'M LOOKING FOR A
THE ONLY THING I KNEW AT THE
"MUKHTAR."
TIME, I'M LOOKING FOR A
SO, WHEN HE SAID "MUKHTAR," IT
"MUKHTAR."
KIND OF, LIKE, CLICKED.
SO, WHEN HE SAID "MUKHTAR," IT
SO I LOOKED AT IT AND I SAID,
KIND OF, LIKE, CLICKED.
"OH, STEVE, YOU GAVE ME THE
SO I LOOKED AT IT AND I SAID,
WRONG PHOTO."
"OH, STEVE, YOU GAVE ME THE
AND I GAVE IT TO STEVE, SO HE
WRONG PHOTO."
WILL KNOW WHO THE MASTERMIND OF
AND I GAVE IT TO STEVE, SO HE
9/11 IS.
WILL KNOW WHO THE MASTERMIND OF
>> Logan: YOU'RE PLAYING IT VERY
9/11 IS.
COOL, BUT WHAT'S GOING THROUGH
>> Logan: YOU'RE PLAYING IT VERY
YOUR HEAD, REALLY?
COOL, BUT WHAT'S GOING THROUGH
>> Soufan: "HOLY ( BLEEP )!
YOUR HEAD, REALLY?
K.S.M. IS AN AL QAEDA GUY, THE
>> Soufan: "HOLY ( BLEEP )!
ONE IN 9/11?"
K.S.M. IS AN AL QAEDA GUY, THE
>> Logan: IT WAS AN ACCIDENT?
ONE IN 9/11?"
>> Soufan: TOTALLY.
>> Logan: IT WAS AN ACCIDENT?
TOTALLY.
>> Soufan: TOTALLY.
>> Logan: SOUFAN SAYS HE
TOTALLY.
BELIEVES ABU ZUBAYDAH DIDN'T
>> Logan: SOUFAN SAYS HE
MEAN TO DIVULGE IMPORTANT
BELIEVES ABU ZUBAYDAH DIDN'T
INFORMATION, AND WAS TRYING TO
MEAN TO DIVULGE IMPORTANT
GIVE UP AS LITTLE AS POSSIBLE.
INFORMATION, AND WAS TRYING TO
WAS HE WELL VERSED IN
GIVE UP AS LITTLE AS POSSIBLE.
>> Logan: ...COUNTER-
WAS HE WELL VERSED IN
INTELLIGENCE?
>> Logan: ...COUNTER-
>> Soufan: YES.
INTELLIGENCE?
HE'S... HE'S DEFINITELY WELL
>> Soufan: YES.
VERSED IN COUNTER-INTELLIGENCE.
HE'S... HE'S DEFINITELY WELL
COUNTER-INTERROGATION.
VERSED IN COUNTER-INTELLIGENCE.
HE IS A SMART... HE IS, I CAN
COUNTER-INTERROGATION.
ACTUALLY SAY, BORDERLINE GENIUS.
HE IS A SMART... HE IS, I CAN
YOU KNOW, I... I HEAR A LOT OF
ACTUALLY SAY, BORDERLINE GENIUS.
PEOPLE SAYING HE'S AN IDIOT.
YOU KNOW, I... I HEAR A LOT OF
HE'S... NO, HE'S... HE'S
PEOPLE SAYING HE'S AN IDIOT.
PROBABLY ONE OF THE SMARTEST
HE'S... NO, HE'S... HE'S
PEOPLE I INTERROGATED.
PROBABLY ONE OF THE SMARTEST
>> Logan: SOUFAN THOUGHT HE AND
PEOPLE I INTERROGATED.
HIS PARTNER WERE MAKING
>> Logan: SOUFAN THOUGHT HE AND
PROGRESS, BUT HE SAYS EVERYTHING
HIS PARTNER WERE MAKING
ABRUPTLY CHANGED AFTER TEN DAYS
PROGRESS, BUT HE SAYS EVERYTHING
WHEN HE WAS TOLD TO STOP TALKING
ABRUPTLY CHANGED AFTER TEN DAYS
TO ABU ZUBAYDAH.
WHEN HE WAS TOLD TO STOP TALKING
>> Soufan: THE C.T.C. TEAM, THE
TO ABU ZUBAYDAH.
COUNTER-TERRORISM CENTER TEAM,
>> Soufan: THE C.T.C. TEAM, THE
ARRIVED.
COUNTER-TERRORISM CENTER TEAM,
>> Logan: OF THE CIA.
ARRIVED.
>> Soufan: OF THE CIA.
>> Logan: OF THE CIA.
SO WE TOLD THEM, FROM OUR
>> Soufan: OF THE CIA.
PERSPECTIVE, THAT HE HAS BEEN
SO WE TOLD THEM, FROM OUR
COOPERATING.
PERSPECTIVE, THAT HE HAS BEEN
WE JUST GOT INFORMATION THAT
COOPERATING.
K.S.M. IS THE MASTERMIND OF
WE JUST GOT INFORMATION THAT
9/11.
K.S.M. IS THE MASTERMIND OF
THEY SAID, "WELL, YEAH, BUT
9/11.
THERE'S A BELIEF THAT THERE'S A
THEY SAID, "WELL, YEAH, BUT
LOT MORE INFORMATION, AND HE'S
THERE'S A BELIEF THAT THERE'S A
NOT GIVING IT UP YET."
LOT MORE INFORMATION, AND HE'S
SO IT ENDED UP THAT THERE'S A
NOT GIVING IT UP YET."
PLAN ALREADY DECIDED IN
SO IT ENDED UP THAT THERE'S A
WASHINGTON THAT WAS BASICALLY TO
PLAN ALREADY DECIDED IN
STRATEGICALLY DIMINISH HIS
WASHINGTON THAT WAS BASICALLY TO
"ABILITY TO RESIST," AS... AS
STRATEGICALLY DIMINISH HIS
THE TERM WAS USED.
"ABILITY TO RESIST," AS... AS
WE KNEW THAT WE'RE GOING DOWN ON
THE TERM WAS USED.
A PATH THAT'S A DANGEROUS PATH,
WE KNEW THAT WE'RE GOING DOWN ON
A PATH THAT WE HAVEN'T BEEN ON
A PATH THAT'S A DANGEROUS PATH,
BEFORE.
A PATH THAT WE HAVEN'T BEEN ON
SO WE HAD TO PULL OUT FROM THE
BEFORE.
INTERROGATION, AND WE HAD TO
SO WE HAD TO PULL OUT FROM THE
START WITNESSING SOMETHING THAT
INTERROGATION, AND WE HAD TO
WAS REALLY SURPRISING, SOME
START WITNESSING SOMETHING THAT
TECHNIQUE THAT WE NEVER THOUGHT
WAS REALLY SURPRISING, SOME
THAT WE WILL SEE US DOING.
TECHNIQUE THAT WE NEVER THOUGHT
>> Logan: THE NEW TECHNIQUES ALI
THAT WE WILL SEE US DOING.
SOUFAN IS TALKING ABOUT INCLUDED
>> Logan: THE NEW TECHNIQUES ALI
NUDITY, SLEEP-DEPRIVATION, AND
SOUFAN IS TALKING ABOUT INCLUDED
LOUD MUSIC.
NUDITY, SLEEP-DEPRIVATION, AND
IT WAS THE BEGINNING OF THE
LOUD MUSIC.
TOUGH AND CONTROVERSIAL METHODS
IT WAS THE BEGINNING OF THE
THAT WOULD ULTIMATELY INCLUDE
TOUGH AND CONTROVERSIAL METHODS
WATER-BOARDING AND BECOME KNOWN
THAT WOULD ULTIMATELY INCLUDE
AS "ENHANCED INTERROGATION
WATER-BOARDING AND BECOME KNOWN
TECHNIQUES."
AS "ENHANCED INTERROGATION
WHAT ALI SOUFAN WITNESSED, AND
TECHNIQUES."
WHAT HE DID ABOUT IT, WHEN WE
WHAT ALI SOUFAN WITNESSED, AND
COME BACK.
>> Logan: THE USE OF WATER-
BOARDING AND OTHER TOUGH NEW
METHODS KNOWN AS "ENHANCED
INTERROGATION TECHNIQUES" LED TO
A VERY PUBLIC DEBATE ABOUT
WHETHER THE U.S. WAS TORTURING
TERRORISM SUSPECTS.
THE VIDEOTAPES OF THOSE
INTERROGATIONS HAVE REPORTEDLY
BEEN DESTROYED, AND HARDLY
ANYONE WHO PARTICIPATED IN THEM
HAS SPOKEN PUBLICLY.
NOR HAS ENOUGH INFORMATION BEEN
MADE PUBLIC TO DETERMINE IF THE
TECHNIQUES WERE SUCCESSFUL.
BUT IN APRIL OF 2002, FBI AGENT
ALI SOUFAN WITNESSED THE
BEGINNING OF THE USE OF THESE
TECHNIQUES ON THE U.S.'s FIRST
HIGH-VALUE TERRORIST DETAINEE,
ABU ZUBAYDAH.
SOUFAN SAYS HE WAS MAKING GOOD
PROGRESS WITH ABU ZUBAYDAH
THROUGH TRADITIONAL METHODS OF
QUESTIONING.
BUT HE WAS TOLD THAT A CIA
CONTRACTOR, HIRED FOR HIS
INTERROGATION EXPERTISE, WOULD
BE TAKING CONTROL.
SOUFAN THEN WATCHED ON A CLOSED
CIRCUIT MONITOR AS A VERY
DIFFERENT APPROACH WAS USED.
>> Soufan: THE PLAN AT THE TIME
WAS TO GO IN AND TELL ABU
ZUBAYDAH ONE QUESTION.
TELL HIM, "TELL ME WHAT I WANT
TO KNOW."
AND IF ABU ZUBAYDAH SAID, "WHAT
DO YOU WANT TO KNOW?" OR ASK ANY
QUESTIONS ABOUT THAT, THE PERSON
IS TO WALK OUT.
AND SAY, "YOU KNOW," AND WALK
OUT.
AND THEN, THEY HAVE A CONTINUUM
OF TECHNIQUES LIKE... YOU KNOW,
IT STARTED WITH, LIKE, NUDITY.
AND THEN, YOU HAVE NOISE AND YOU
HAVE SLEEP DEPRIVATION.
AND IT GOES FROM ONE STAGE TO
ANOTHER, UNTIL HE DECIDES TO
COOPERATE.
>> Logan: THIS INDIVIDUAL, WHY
WERE THEY PUT IN CHARGE?
>> Soufan: I DON'T KNOW.
SUPPOSEDLY, HE'S AN EXPERT IN
THE FIELD.
SO I ASK HIM, "DO YOU KNOW
ANYTHING ABOUT ISLAMIC
FUNDAMENTALISM?"
HE SAID, "NO."
"HAVE YOU EVER INTERROGATED
ANYBODY?"
"NO."
HE BASICALLY SAID, NO, HE KNOWS
HUMAN NATURE.
>> Logan: AND HOW DOES ABU
ZUBAYDAH REACT TO THIS?
>> Soufan: HE BASICALLY STOPPED
COOPERATING.
>> Logan: THE INFORMATION DRIED
UP?
>> Soufan: YES, TOTALLY.
>> Logan: SOUFAN SAYS THAT,
AFTER SEVERAL DAYS WITH NOTHING
FROM ABU ZUBAYDAH, HE AND HIS
PARTNER AND A CIA INTERROGATOR
WERE ALLOWED TO START TALKING TO
HIM ONCE AGAIN.
AND THEY OBTAINED INFORMATION
THAT LED THE CIA AND THE FBI TO
CAPTURE THIS MAN, JOSE PADILLA,
THE AMERICAN CITIZEN ACCUSED OF
PLOTTING TO SET OFF A "DIRTY
BOMB" IN THE U.S.
SO YOUR FEELING IS, AT THIS
POINT, THAT YOUR TECHNIQUE
HAS... HAS STARTED TO WORK
AGAIN?
>> Soufan: WE... WE'RE BACK.
YEAH, NO, WE'RE BACK.
AND... AND MORE INFORMATION
STARTS COMING.
AND THEN, SUDDENLY, OUT OF THE
BLUE, THEY SAID, "WAIT A SECOND.
YOU GUYS ARE GOING TO BE OUT,
BECAUSE WE BELIEVE HE'S NOT
COOPERATING ANYMORE," WHICH WAS
REALLY SHOCKING FOR US TO HEAR.
>> Logan: SO WHAT DID YOU DO?
>> Soufan: WHAT CAN WE DO?
WE'RE WATCHING TIME PASS BY WITH
NOBODY TALKING TO A DETAINEE,
DAY AFTER DAY.
>> Logan: NO ONE EVEN SPOKE TO
HIM?
>> Soufan: NO, THEY GO IN.
THEY SAY, "TELL ME WHAT I WANT
TO KNOW."
HE SAYS, "WHAT DO YOU WANT TO
KNOW?"
AND YOU WALK OUT, PERIOD.
THAT'S IT.
THAT'S THE WHOLE INTERROGATION
"PLAN," IF YOU WANT TO CALL IT.
>> Logan: SO THERE'S SOMETHING
THAT HAPPENS.
IT ESCALATES TO A POINT WHERE
YOU DECIDE, THAT'S IT, YOU'RE
LEAVING.
WHAT IS IT?
>> Soufan: THERE WAS A
CONFINEMENT BOX.
>> Logan: THAT SOUNDS LIKE A
COFFIN.
>> Soufan: UH... "CONFINEMENT
BOX," AND I CAME ONE DAY, AND I
SAW IT IN THE FACILITY.
AND I THOUGHT, AT THE TIME, "WE
HAD THE GUY COOPERATING.
SO WHAT'S GOING ON?"
I MEAN, THAT BOX WAS NOT MADE
OVERNIGHT.
THERE'S SOMETHING GOING ON AND
WE DON'T KNOW ABOUT.
>> Logan: WHAT WAS THE BOX FOR?
>> Soufan: I DON'T KNOW.
I MEAN, DEFINITELY, IT'S... IT'S
FOR... FOR ABU ZUBAYDAH.
>> Logan: BUT THAT WAS NOT THE
KIND OF TECHNIQUE THAT YOU WERE
PREPARED TO STICK AROUND FOR?
>> Soufan: NO.
I JUST FELT THAT, LITERALLY,
"WE'RE PLAYING GAMES, AND I
REALLY CANNOT BE PART OF THIS."
>> Logan: SOUFAN CLAIMS HE
WASN'T THE ONLY PERSON THAT FELT
THAT WAY.
>> Soufan: AT LEAST ONE OF THE
CIA GUYS SAID, "YOU KNOW WHAT?
THAT'S NOT WORTH IT.
I'M NOT GOING TO DO THIS."
HE LEFT.
HE LEFT THE LOCATION...
>> Logan: ANOTHER CIA AGENT ON
THE GROUND?
>> Soufan: YEAH.
ACTUALLY, HE LEFT BEFORE ME.
AND THEN... AND THEN WE FINALLY
REPORTED TO HEADQUARTERS THAT,
YOU KNOW, "THIS IS WHAT'S
HAPPENING," AS I CALLED IT IN
THE D.O.J.-- DEPARTMENT OF
JUSTICE INSPECTOR GENERAL--
REPORT, "BORDERLINE TORTURE."
AND-- FBI HEADQUARTERS SAID,
"YOU KNOW... YOU KNOW WE DON'T
DO THAT, JUST..."
AND, EVENTUALLY, AFTER THAT,
THEY PULLED ALL FBI AGENTS FROM
HIGH-VALUE DETAINEES
INTERROGATIONS.
>> Logan: SOUFAN NEVER SAW ABU
ZUBAYDAH AGAIN, AND ONLY
OCCASIONALLY SAW THESE
TECHNIQUES BEING USED AFTER
THAT, BUT HE CLAIMS THAT WHEN
PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH ADDRESSED
THE NATION IN 2006, THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE WERE BEING MISLED.
>> President George Bush: WE
KNEW THAT ZUBAYDAH HAD MORE
INFORMATION THAT COULD SAVE
INNOCENT LIVES, BUT HE STOPPED
TALKING.
IT BECAME CLEAR THAT HE HAD
RECEIVED TRAINING ON HOW TO
RESIST INTERROGATION.
AND SO THE CIA USED AN
ALTERNATIVE SET OF PROCEDURES.
>> Soufan: I THINK SOMEBODY TOLD
THE PRESIDENT SOME FAKE
INFORMATION, SOME FALSE
INFORMATION.
ZUBAYDAH DID NOT STOP TALKING;
INTRODUCING THE TECHNIQUES MADE
HIM STOP TALKING.
>> Logan: SOUFAN ARGUES THAT
TERRORISTS LIKE ABU ZUBAYDAH
HAVE BEEN TRAINED TO EXPECT
EXTREMELY BRUTAL TREATMENT IN
MIDDLE EASTERN PRISONS, WHICH IS
ONE REASON HE BELIEVES ENHANCED
INTERROGATION TECHNIQUES ARE NOT
EFFECTIVE.
>> Soufan: IF YOU LOOK AT THEM
FROM AN AMERICAN PERSPECTIVE,
YOU WILL SAY, "WOW, THAT'S
TORTURE."
BUT REALLY, THAT'S LIKE SAYING
HELLO IN SOME JAIL IN THE MIDDLE
EAST.
I MEAN, THE... LITERALLY, THIS
IS NOT THE TORTURE THAT THESE
GUYS ARE EXPECTING.
SO WHY DO WE START GOING ON A
PATH THAT EVENTUALLY WE'RE GOING
TO HIT A GLASS CEILING?
AND WHEN YOU HIT THE GLASS
CEILING, WHAT DO YOU DO?
>> Logan: WHAT DO YOU DO?
>> Soufan: THE DETAINEE CALLS
YOUR BLUFF.
YOU CANNOT GO BACK AND SAY, "I'M
GOING TO BUILD A RAPPORT."
THAT'S WHY YOU KEEP REPEATING
THE GLASS CEILING AGAIN AND
AGAIN AND AGAIN AND AGAIN.
ABU ZUBAYDAH WAS WATER-BOARDED
83 TIMES; KHALID SHEIKH
MOHAMMED, 183 TIMES.
WHAT DOES THAT TELL YOU?
DOES THAT TELL YOU THE TECHNIQUE
IS WORKING?
>> Logan: A NUMBER OF PEOPLE IN
THE CIA AND THE INTELLIGENCE
COMMUNITY TOLD US THAT ABU
ZUBAYDAH DID GIVE UP INFORMATION
AFTER HE WAS WATER-BOARDED,
WHICH THEY SAY HELPED SAVE
AMERICAN LIVES, AND THAT, ALL
MORAL QUESTIONS ASIDE, THE
ENHANCED INTERROGATION PROGRAM
YIELDED SIGNIFICANT
INTELLIGENCE, INCLUDING
INFORMATION THAT CONTRIBUTED TO
THE KILLING OF OSAMA BIN LADEN.
AT LEAST TWO FORMER DIRECTORS OF
THE CIA, GEORGE TENET AND
MICHAEL HAYDEN, SAY THAT
ENHANCED INTERROGATION
TECHNIQUES DO WORK.
>> Soufan: SURE, SURE.
>> Logan: THEY HAVE ACCESS TO
MORE INTELLIGENCE THAN YOU.
>> Soufan: ABSOLUTELY.
>> Logan: IF YOU DON'T KNOW
EVERYTHING, HOW CAN YOU BE SO
SURE THAT THEY DON'T WORK?
>> Soufan: BECAUSE I AM PRIVY TO
A LOT OF INFORMATION THAT ALSO
I'M NOT TELLING YOU HERE.
>> Logan: BUT IS IT POSSIBLE FOR
YOU TO KNOW ALL THE INFORMATION,
EVERYTHING THAT MAY OR MAY NOT
HAVE BEEN GAINED FROM THESE
TECHNIQUES?
>> Soufan: I'M NOT CLAIMING THAT
I KNOW EVERYTHING.
I KNOW WHAT I KNOW.
>> Logan: THE ONE THING THAT HAS
CAUSED ALI SOUFAN MORE ANGUISH
THAN ANYTHING ELSE IS THE
THOUGHT THAT THE EVENTS OF 9/11
MIGHT HAVE BEEN PREVENTED-- IF,
HE SAYS, THE CIA HAD SHARED
CERTAIN INFORMATION WITH HIM AND
HIS FBI TEAM.
WHILE THEY WERE INVESTIGATING
THE ATTACK ON THE U.S.S. "COLE"
IN NOVEMBER 2000, SOUFAN'S TEAM
LEARNED THAT THIS AL QAEDA
OPERATIVE HAD MET WITH OTHER
TERRORISTS IN ASIA AND RECEIVED
A LARGE SUM OF MONEY.
SOUFAN SAYS HE ASKED THE CIA IF
IT KNEW WHAT THIS OPERATIVE WAS
UP TO.
YOU MADE THREE FORMAL REQUESTS
TO THE CIA...
>> Soufan: THERE WAS THREE
FORMAL REQUESTS.
>> Logan: ...THROUGH THE FBI
CHAIN?
>> Soufan: RIGHT.
>> Logan: AND TIME AND AGAIN,
THE CIA TELL YOU WHAT?
>> Soufan: THEY DON'T KNOW
ANYTHING.
>> Logan: BUT SOUFAN SAYS HE
LATER LEARNED THE CIA KNEW,
EIGHT MONTHS BEFORE 9/11, THAT
THIS SAME OPERATIVE HAD MET IN
MALAYSIA WITH TWO TERRORISM
SUSPECTS WHO WOULD LATER HIJACK
THE PLANE THAT CRASHED INTO THE
PENTAGON.
AND THE CIA ALSO KNEW THAT THOSE
TWO SUSPECTS WERE HEADING TO THE
U.S.
>> Soufan: THE AGENCY KNEW THAT
THESE AL QAEDA OPERATIVES IN
SOUTHEAST ASIA FLEW TO AMERICA,
OR THEY HAVE VISAS TO COME TO
THE UNITED STATES, AND SOMEBODY
DECIDED, "LET'S NOT SHARE THE
INFORMATION."
>> Logan: AND IF IT HAD BEEN
SHARED WITH YOU, WHAT THEN?
>> Soufan: I TRY NOT TO THINK
ABOUT THAT.
I TRY NOT TO THINK ABOUT...
ABOUT WHAT COULD HAVE HAPPENED.
MAYBE... MAYBE THOUSANDS OF
AMERICAN LIVES WILL BE SPARED,
MAYBE.
>> Logan: THE CIA TOLD US ANY
SUGGESTION IT PURPOSELY REFUSED
TO SHARE CRITICAL INFORMATION ON
THE 9/11 PLOTS WITH THE FBI IS
"BASELESS" AND "THESE
ALLEGATIONS DIMINISH THE HARD
WORK AND DEDICATION OF COUNTLESS
CIA OFFICERS."
ALI SOUFAN LEFT THE FBI SIX
YEARS AGO AND, TODAY, HE RUNS A
SECURITY CONSULTING COMPANY
BASED IN NEW YORK.
HE TOLD US HE HASN'T BEEN TO
GROUND ZERO SINCE THE FIRST
ANNIVERSARY OF 9/11, AND THERE'S
A REASON FOR THAT.
>> Soufan: MAYBE I'M ONE OF
THESE PEOPLE WHO DIDN'T GET OVER
IT.
>> Logan: CAN YOU TELL ME WHY?
>> Soufan: YOU KNOW, MAYBE PART
OF ME FEELS GUILTY.
MAYBE PART OF ME FEELS SOME SORT
OF RESPONSIBILITY OF WHAT
HAPPENED.
>> Logan: BUT YOU DID YOUR BEST.
YOU GAVE YOUR ALL.
WHY WOULD YOU FEEL GUILTY?
>> Soufan: IF YOU WANT TO BE
TRUTHFUL WITH YOURSELF, VERY
DIFFICULT WHAT YOU FEEL... AND
NOT TO KIND OF LIKE FEEL THAT,
YOU KNOW, "MAYBE I COULD'VE DONE
SOMETHING."
>> Logan: IS THAT WHY IT'S HARD
FOR YOU TO GO TO GROUND ZERO?
>> Soufan: YEAH.
ACTUALLY, I WENT THERE ONCE, ON
THE... THE FIRST ANNIVERSARY,
BUT THAT'S IT.
>> Logan: IT'S HARD FOR ANYONE
TO GO THERE, BUT... BUT...
>> Soufan: YEAH, ABSOLUTELY.
>> Logan: WHY SO HARD FOR YOU,
ALI?
>> Soufan: I DON'T KNOW.
I DON'T KNOW.
>> Pelley: ON 9/11, DR. BENJAMIN
LUFT PREPARED STONY BROOK
UNIVERSITY MEDICAL CENTER ON
LONG ISLAND FOR THE MASSIVE
NUMBER OF CASUALTIES HE EXPECTED
TO OVERWHELM THE EMERGENCY ROOM.
BUT NONE CAME THROUGH THE DOOR
THAT DAY, SO FEW HAD SURVIVED.
AS IT TURNED OUT, DR. LUFT'S
CASUALTIES WERE COMING, BUT THEY
WOULD ARRIVE MUCH LATER.
ALTHOUGH NEARLY 3,000 PEOPLE
WERE KILLED AT THE WORLD TRADE
CENTER, 70,000 OTHERS RESPONDED
TO GROUND ZERO AND WORKED FOR
MONTHS AMID TOXIC SMOKE AND
DUST.
DR. LUFT HELPED START A CLINIC
TO TREAT THE CHRONIC ILLNESSES
AND PSYCHOLOGICAL TRAUMA
SUFFERED BY THE 9/11 RESPONDERS.
OVER TIME, LUFT DISCOVERED
SOMETHING THAT HE NEVER
EXPECTED-- HE BEGAN TO HEAR
THEIR STORIES; HONEST, RAW,
IRREPLACEABLE STORIES.
AND ALMOST TWO YEARS AGO, HE
BEGAN TO RECORD THE DEFINITIVE
HISTORY OF GROUND ZERO,
REMEMBERING 9/11 IN THE WORDS OF
THE PEOPLE WHO LIVED IT.
>> Dr. Benjamin Luft: THE
PROBLEM THAT CAME UP WAS THAT
OUR SOCIETY BEGAN TO LOOK AT THE
RESPONDERS IN TERMS OF THEIR
DISEASE.
THEY BECAME AN ISSUE IN TERMS OF
THEIR LIABILITY.
AND MY FEELING WAS THAT THAT'S
NOT WHO THE RESPONDERS WERE.
LET'S FIND OUT WHO THEY ARE AS
HUMAN BEINGS-- WHAT THEIR
MOTIVATION WAS, WHAT VALUES THEY
HAD, WHAT SACRIFICES THEY MADE,
HOW THEY WERE ABLE TO RENEW
THEMSELVES.
IT WAS ALMOST TAKE... LIKE
TAKING A CIVICS CLASS AS TO WHAT
IS IMPORTANT ABOUT BEING A
CITIZEN.
WHAT IS IMPORTANT ABOUT BEING A
HUMAN BEING?
WHAT IS IMPORTANT TO BEING AN
AMERICAN?
>> Stacey Goodman: I WORKED AT
THE MAKESHIFT MORGUE.
WE TOOK IN ALL THE BODIES, YOU
KNOW?
SAYING, "I'M SORRY FOR YOUR
LOSS" WAS VERY DIFFICULT,
BECAUSE THAT ALMOST GOT TO BE
LIKE ROTE, YOU KNOW?
>> Pelley: STACEY GOODMAN, A
POLICE DETECTIVE, IS ONE OF THE
VOICES DR. LUFT RECORDED IN WHAT
IS NOW CALLED THE WORLD TRADE
CENTER ORAL HISTORY PROJECT.
>> Goodman: AT ONE POINT, THIS
SENIOR... I THINK HE WAS A
RETIRED FIREMAN, HE COMES IN.
HIS HANDS ARE CUPPED.
AND HE'S GOT BONES IN HIS HANDS.
AND HE GOES UP TO THE MEDICAL
EXAMINER AND HE PUTS THE BONES
IN FRONT OF HIM AND HE GOES,
"THIS IS MY SON."
WHAT DO YOU SAY TO THAT?
( SNIFFS )
>> Pelley: NO ONE COULD POSSIBLY
KNOW 9/11 THE WAY THESE PEOPLE
DO.
WE ASKED SEVERAL OF THE
RESPONDERS TO GIVE US A SENSE OF
THE HOURS OF TESTIMONY THAT
THEY'VE PUT INTO DR. LUFT'S
PROJECT.
>> Carol Paukner: THE DEBRIS AND
THE PEOPLE RUSHING OUT AT US, I
COULDN'T EVEN MAKE IT TO TOWER
ONE.
I MADE IT TO THE BASE OF TOWER
TWO.
>> Pelley: CAROL PAUKNER WAS A
COP, ON THE SCENE BEFORE THE
TOWERS FELL.
>> Paukner: THIS BIG, BRAWLY FBI
GUY HAD HIS SHIELD AROUND HIS
NECK.
AND, YOU KNOW, I LOOKED UP AT
HIM AND HE'S TELLING... THERE
WAS ABOUT SIX OFFICERS THERE
WITH ME, AND HE'S LIKE, "IF YOU
WANT TO LIVE, YOU... YOU MIGHT
AS WELL LEAVE NOW."
HE SAID, "WE'RE ALL GOING TO
DIE."
AND I'M LIKE, "I CAN'T... WE
CAN'T LEAVE.
I'M... I'M NOT LEAVING."
AND THE OFFICERS THAT I WERE
THERE WITH, "WE'RE NOT LEAVING,
EITHER."
AND WE CONTINUED TO EVACUATE AND
DO OUR JOBS BUT, YOU KNOW, WE
WERE ALL LIKE, "WOW, WE'RE GOING
TO DIE," YOU KNOW?
>> Pelley: PAUKNER WAS TRAPPED
WHEN THE FIRST TOWER COLLAPSED.
THAT'S HER, ON THE LEFT, AFTER
SHE PULLED HERSELF OUT OF THE
WRECKAGE.
SHE'S WITH A FELLOW COP AND A
WOMAN THAT THEY RESCUED.
>> Richard Doerler: I WAS ONE OF
THE GUYS WHO WAS ABLE TO PULL
SOMEONE OUT ALIVE.
>> Pelley: SO FEW WERE SAVED,
BUT POLICE SERGEANT RICHARD
DOERLER HELPED PULL OUT ONE RARE
SURVIVOR, A FELLOW COP NAMED
JOHN McLOUGHLIN.
>> Doerler: THEY WERE GIVING...
JOHN WAS... GIVING JOHN
McLOUGHLIN MORPHINE BECAUSE
THE... THE PLAN WAS THAT, IF WE
COULDN'T EXTRICATE HIM, THEY
WERE GOING TO CUT HIS LEGS OFF.
JOHN SCREAMED IN PAIN WHILE WE
PULLED HIM, INITIALLY, SO WE LET
HIM REST.
AND WE SIMULTANEOUSLY PULLED
AGAIN AND WE BROKE HIM FREE AND
PULLED HIM OUT.
>> Luft: WANT YOU TAKE SOME NICE
DEEP BREATHS.
>> Pelley: BENJAMIN LUFT IS A
MEDICAL DOCTOR WHO VOLUNTEERED
TO HELP CREATE A CLINIC FOR THE
9/11 RESPONDERS AT STONY BROOK
UNIVERSITY MEDICAL CENTER, PART
OF THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW
YORK.
MORE THAN 6,000 RESPONDERS
ENROLLED IN HIS WORLD TRADE
CENTER HEALTH PROGRAM.
ONE STUDY SHOWS THAT NEARLY A
THIRD OF THOSE WHO WORKED AT
GROUND ZERO HAVE ASTHMA, 42%
SUFFER WITH SINUSITIS, NEARLY
40% HAVE GASTRO-ESOPHAGEAL
REFLUX DISEASE, KNOWN AS "GERD";
AND MANY HAVE REACTIVE AIRWAYS
DYSFUNCTION SYNDROME THAT THE
PATIENTS JUST CALL "RADS."
>> Luft: WHEN YOU'RE A PHYSICIAN
AND YOU SEE PATIENTS, YOU TEND
TO REDUCE THEM TO THEIR SYMPTOMS
AND SIGNS, TO THEIR MEDICAL
CONDITIONS.
AND THAT'S HOW YOU THINK OF
THEM.
>> Pelley: LUFT LISTENED TO
THEIR STORIES IN THE EXAMINING
ROOM FOR EIGHT YEARS WHEN HE
REALIZED THAT HIS PATIENTS WERE
THE AUTHORS OF ONE OF THE MOST
DRAMATIC CHAPTERS OF AMERICAN
HISTORY.
>> Luft: YOUR STORY OF WHAT
HAPPENED ON 9/11.
>> SHE BECAME HYSTERICAL.
SHE GOT A CELL PHONE CALL THAT
HER... THAT THE TRADE CENTER WAS
HIT WITH A PLANE.
>> Pelley: WITH HIS OWN MONEY, A
FEW DONATIONS, AND A SMALL,
MOSTLY VOLUNTEER STAFF, LUFT
STARTED HIS INTERVIEWS.
SO FAR, HE'S RECORDED 137.
>> Paukner: WHEN THE BUILDING
IMPLODED DOWN, IT BLEW ME OUT OF
THE BUILDING, AND I WAS ABLE TO
HOLD ONTO THE DOORWAY WITH MY
LEFT ARM.
>> Christine Famiglietti: THE
FIRST THING I FOUND WAS AN
ENTIRE BODY, BURNED INTO REBAR.
>> Bill Fischer: THEY... THEY
PUT A LINE AROUND OUR WAIST.
I'M LIKE, "I'M GOING IN THIS
WAY, SNAKING AROUND ON MY BELLY
AROUND," SAYS, "THERE'S NO WAY
YOU CAN PULL ME OUT."
AND THE GUY JUST LOOKED AT ME.
IT WASN'T TO PULL US OUT; IT WAS
JUST TO FIND US IF WE DIED.
>> WHERE WE EXPECTED TO SEE TWO
TALL BUILDINGS, WE JUST SAW A
SKELETON.
THE MOST POWERFUL NATION IN THE
WORLD.
HOW COULD THIS HAPPEN?
>> Luft: THERE'S NO CLEARER
RENDITION OF WHAT HAPPENED ON
9/11 THAN THERE ARE IN THESE
HISTORIES.
>> Pelley: WHO ARE THESE PEOPLE?
>> Luft: SO, OF COURSE, WE HAVE
THE FIREMEN AND THE POLICEMEN
AND THE E.M.S. WORKERS.
AND THEN, WE HAVE THE VOLUNTEER
FIREMEN.
AND THEN, YOU HAVE THE
IRONWORKERS AND THE CONSTRUCTION
WORKERS AND THE LABORERS.
ON 9/11, ALL AMERICANS
RESPONDED, FROM ALL WALKS OF
LIFE.
>> I WAS A SENIOR IN HIGH
SCHOOL.
I REALIZED I HAD TO GO DOWN
THERE.
I DON'T KNOW HOW I'M GOING TO
HELP; I DON'T KNOW WHAT I CAN
DO.
>> MY WHOLE FAMILY IS COPS.
I'M THE 13TH IN MY FAMILY BEING
A NEW YORK CITY POLICE OFFICER.
>> I AM A LICENSED MASSAGE
THERAPIST.
I JUST FELT LIKE I HAD TO BE
DOWN THERE HELPING THESE PEOPLE,
KNOWING WHAT I DO FOR A LIVING
CAN HELP THESE PEOPLE.
>> I WORK FOR THE N.Y.C. HIGHWAY
DEPT.
I.... YOU KNOW, ROADWORK,
CONSTRUCTION, STUFF LIKE THAT.
I NEVER TRAINED FOR ANYTHING
LIKE THIS.
AND I LEARNED QUICK, THOUGH.
>> Pelley: WE SPENT A FEW HOURS
WITH SOME OF THE RESPONDERS AT
STONY BROOK UNIVERSITY.
AND AS WE LISTENED, WE REALIZED
THAT, FOR THEM, TODAY, SUNDAY,
ISN'T THE TENTH ANNIVERSARY OF
SOMETHING THAT HAPPENED; IT'S
THE TENTH YEAR OF SOMETHING THAT
NEVER ENDS.
IN A SENSE, IT'S ALWAYS 9/11.
JOHN GALLAGHER IS A FORMER NEW
YORK CITY FIRE CAPTAIN SUFFERING
WITH PULMONARY FIBROSIS,
SCARRING OF THE LUNGS THAT ONLY
GETS WORSE.
>> John Gallagher: THE WORLD
TRADE CENTER IS STILL CLAIMING
LIVES.
PEOPLE HAVE HAD THEIR LIVES
SHORTENED.
PEOPLE HAVE LOST THEIR FATHERS,
THEIR... THEIR MOTHERS TO
CANCERS, TO LUNG DISEASES,
ANYTHING THAT YOU CAN IMAGINE,
BLOOD-BORNE DISEASES.
PEOPLE ARE STILL DYING.
>> Pelley: SHOW OF HANDS.
HOW MANY OF YOU HAVE BEEN LIVING
THROUGH MEDICAL PROBLEMS AS A
RESULT OF THE WORK THAT YOU DID
IN THOSE DAYS?
ALMOST ALL OF YOU.
BILL, GIVE ME A SENSE OF WHAT
YOU'VE BEEN WORKING THROUGH,
HEALTH-WISE.
>> Fischer: I HAVE ASTHMA, I
HAVE NODULES ON BOTH LUNGS,
SINUSITIS, RHINITIS.
>> Pelley: BILL FISCHER WAS A
NEW YORK CITY COP, NOW RETIRED.
>> Fischer: I... I NEVER SMOKED,
I DON'T DRINK.
I'M... I GO THE GYM AS OFTEN AS
I CAN, AND IT'S NOT AS MUCH AS I
WOULD LIKE TO ANYMORE.
I LITERALLY HAVE A BUCKET OF
ABOUT 20 MEDICINES, A PLASTIC
BUCKET THAT I HAVE TO TAKE
SOMETHING DURING THE DAY.
>> Pelley: THIS IS BILL FISCHER.
HE WORKED AT GROUND ZERO FOR
FOUR MONTHS.
AND LIKE THOUSANDS OF OTHERS, HE
WAS COVERED IN DUST THAT
CONTAINED CARCINOGENS, ASBESTOS,
AND TOXINS TOO NUMEROUS TO LIST.
KEN GEORGE WAS THERE, TOO.
HE HELPED RECOVER HUMAN REMAINS.
KEN, WHAT... WHAT HAS YOUR
HEALTH EXPERIENCE BEEN?
>> Ken George: OH, I GOT A LIST.
>> Pelley: EVERYBODY'S GOT A
LIST, IT SOUNDS LIKE.
>> George: IT STARTED WITH THE
9/11 COUGH I HAD, WHICH LED ME
TO HAVE RADS-- RESTRICTED AIRWAY
DISEASE-- WHICH MEANS I CAN'T
GET ENOUGH OXYGEN IN OR OUT.
LIKE THESE PEOPLE SAID, THE
SINUSES, I HAVE ALL THAT.
SO IT'S JUST STARTED SNOWBALLING
OUT OF CONTROL, YOU KNOW WHAT I
MEAN?
AND WHO KNOWS IF, FIVE YEARS
DOWN THE LINE, IF I'M GOING TO
WIND UP WITH CANCER, YOU KNOW.
I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE I'M...
MY FAMILY'S TAKEN CARE OF, IF
ANYTHING HAPPENS, YOU KNOW?
I JUST DON'T WANT THEM TO BE OUT
ON THE STREET.
>> Luft: ANY PAIN?
>> Pelley: PAYING THEIR MEDICAL
BILLS HAS BEEN A STRUGGLE.
FUNDING FOR THE WORLD TRADE
CENTER HEALTH PROGRAM WAS NEVER
CERTAIN UNTIL THIS YEAR, WHEN
CONGRESS GUARANTEED COVERAGE.
BUT THAT GUARANTEE LASTS ONLY
THE NEXT FIVE YEARS; THE
ILLNESSES AND THE MENTAL TRAUMA
ARE LIKELY TO LAST A LIFETIME.
>> Tyree Bacon: ONE THING
NOBODY'S MENTIONED, BUT WE ALL
HAVE IT-- IT'S LIKE LUGGAGE AND
WE HAVE IT FOREVER-- IS THE
POST-TRAUMATIC STRESS.
>> Paukner: YEP.
>> Pelley: TYREE BACON WAS A
SENIOR COURT OFFICER WHO WORKED
TEN BLOCKS FROM THE WORLD TRADE
CENTER.
HE REACHED THE TOWERS BEFORE
THEY COLLAPSED.
>> Bacon: THOSE OF US WHO WEAR
UNIFORMS MAKE A LIVING OUT OF
THE WORST TEN MINUTES OF
EVERYBODY'S LIVES.
9/11 WAS A HELL OF A LOT LONGER
THAN TEN MINUTES LONG.
POST-TRAUMATIC STRESS IS
SOMETHING THAT I HAVE A ISSUE
WITH.
SPENT A MONTH AFTER BEING CAUGHT
IN THE COLLAPSE, WAKING UP ON
THE FLOOR, TRYING TO FEEL MY...
MY WAY OUT OF MY OWN BEDROOM.
THAT WENT ON FOR OVER A MONTH.
>> Pelley: THIS IS TYREE BACON,
IN THE ORAL HISTORY PROJECT,
REMEMBERING A WOMAN WHO GRABBED
HIM BY THE SHIRT AS ONE OF THE
TOWERS FELL.
>> Bacon: AND I TOLD HER, I
SAID, "SWEETHEART, DON'T WORRY,
I PROMISE WE'RE GETTING OUT OF
HERE."
I FLAT-OUT LIED TO HER.
I THOUGHT WE WERE GOING TO DIE
WHERE WE WERE.
IF I DIDN'T HAVE HER, I PROBABLY
WOULD'VE CURLED UP IN A FETAL
POSITION AND JUST WAITED TO DIE.
>> Luft: WHEN THAT RESPONDER
WENT DOWN TO GROUND ZERO, THEY
WERE EXPERIENCING TRAUMATIC
EVENTS IN RAPID SUCCESSION:
BUILDINGS FALLING, GIRDERS
FALLING, TRIPPING, YOU KNOW,
PEOPLE JUMPING OUT OF BUILDINGS,
SEEING TREMENDOUS AMOUNTS OF
CARNAGE.
>> Pelley: THE FIRES.
>> Luft: THE FIRES.
NOW, IT'S NOT OCCURRING OVER A
TEN-SECOND PERIOD OF TIME; IT'S
OCCURRING OVER WEEKS AND MONTHS.
AND THE SAME PERSON IS
EXPERIENCING IT OVER AND OVER
AND OVER AGAIN.
>> Paukner: THE JUMPERS, I
THINK, WERE THE WORST, YOU KNOW?
TO ACTUALLY SEE THEM JUMP AND...
AND PULVERIZE JUST IN FRONT OF
YOU, YOU KNOW?
THAT WAS JUST HORRIBLE.
>> Pelley: THERE WAS A SOUND...
>> Paukner: YEAH.
>> Pelley: ...THAT THAT MADE.
>> Paukner: THAT WAS, FIRST... I
DIDN'T KNOW WHAT THAT SOUND WAS,
AT FIRST.
AND THEN, YOU GO TO SEE WHAT
THAT SOUND WAS, AND YOU REALIZE
THAT IT WAS A PERSON THAT HAD
JUST JUMPED.
IF IT'S THAT BAD UP THERE THAT
YOU HAVE TO JUMP, YOU KNOW?
A LOT WE COULDN'T SEE.
>> Luft: ALMOST INVARIABLY,
PEOPLE COME TO US AFTERWARDS AND
SAY, "YOU KNOW, DOC, THIS IS THE
FIRST TIME THAT I'VE BEEN ABLE
TO TALK ABOUT THIS.
THIS IS THE FIRST TIME THAT I
CAN TELL OTHERS WHAT REALLY
HAPPENED ON 9/11."
>> Gallagher: IN THE THREE
MONTHS THAT I WAS THERE, WE
FOUND VERY, VERY FEW VICTIMS.
WE FOUND PIECES, BUT NOT BODIES.
THAT WAS THE FIRST TIME I EVER
SPOKE OF MY EXPERIENCES AT 9/11.
I FOUND IT THERAPEUTIC.
>> Pelley: HOW MANY YEARS WAS IT
THAT YOU DIDN'T TALK ABOUT 9/11?
>> Gallagher: SEVEN YEARS.
>> Pelley: WHY?
>> Gallagher: I DIDN'T WANT TO
REPLAY IT AND I DIDN'T WANT
TO... YOU KNOW, I LIVED IT.
I DIDN'T WANT TO RELIVE IT.
>> Christine Famiglietti: I
DIDN'T THINK IT WAS A SUCH A
GREAT IDEA, BECAUSE I THINK A
LOT OF US BURIED THAT DAY.
>> Pelley: CHRISTINE FAMIGLIETTI
WAS A NEW YORK CITY COP, NOW
RETIRED.
>> Famiglietti: TO REALLY BRING
IT UP AND HASH IT UP AND DISCUSS
IN DEPTH WAS A LITTLE... I WAS A
LITTLE FEARFUL OF THAT.
IN THE LONG RUN, I WAS GLAD I
DID IT.
>> Bacon: THAT'S HOW I'VE GOTTEN
THROUGH MY PTSD IS BY TALKING
ABOUT IT.
AND SOMETIMES IT'S DIFFICULT,
SOMETIMES IT'S NOT, BUT IT'S
HELPED ME A GREAT DEAL TALKING
ABOUT IT; YOU KNOW, HELPS ME
SLEEP AT NIGHT.
>> Pelley: I THINK A LOT OF
FOLKS AT HOME WOULD LIKE TO
KNOW, AFTER TEN YEARS, WOULD YOU
CONSIDER... IN TERMS OF THEIR
MENTAL HEALTH, WOULD YOU
CONSIDER A LOT OF THESE PATIENTS
TO BE BETTER?
>> Luft: I DO BELIEVE THAT THEY
ARE BETTER FROM THE POINT OF
VIEW OF MOVING ON WITH THEIR
LIVES AND BE... HAVING BECOME
MUCH MORE ADAPTABLE.
BUT I DON'T THINK THEY EVER LET
IT... LEAVE IT BEHIND.
IT'S A CONSTANT PART OF THEIR
LIFE.
I THINK THAT THAT'S TRUE FOR ANY
GREAT EVENT THAT OCCURS, BUT
ESPECIALLY TRUE FOR THIS EVENT,
WHICH WAS ETCHED INTO THEIR
CONSCIOUSNESS.
>> Pelley: DR. LUFT'S INTERVIEWS
ARE NOW A DOCUMENTARY, AND ALSO
A BOOK CALLED "WE'RE NOT
LEAVING," THE MEMORABLE QUOTE
FROM OFFICER CAROL PAUKNER TO
THAT FBI AGENT WHO HAD URGED HER
TO RUN.
THE PROFITS WILL GO TO
SCHOLARSHIPS AND JOB TRAINING
FOR THE RESPONDERS AND THEIR
FAMILIES.
JOHN FEAL WAS A DEMOLITION
EXPERT WHO HELPED MOVE THE
WRECKAGE.
>> John Feal: THESE MEN AND
WOMEN TO THE LEFT AND RIGHT OF
ME AND BEHIND ME, THEY'RE THE
BEST OF THE BEST OF WHAT AMERICA
OFFERED TEN YEARS AGO.
WE CAN'T CHANGE HISTORY, AND
THROUGH THEIR EYES, THEY'RE
TELLING AMERICA WHAT THEY SEEN,
WHAT THEY DID, AND WHAT THEY'RE
GOING THROUGH TEN YEARS LATER.
AND... AND THAT IS PRICELESS.
>> Pelley: NOW, THE LIBRARY OF
CONGRESS IS LOOKING INTO ADDING
THE INTERVIEWS TO ITS PERMANENT
COLLECTION, TO BE KEPT FOR ALL
TIME SO THAT GENERATIONS CAN
HEAR THE UNEDITED, UNVARNISHED
REALITY AS EXPERIENCED BY THE
PEOPLE WHO WERE THERE.
>> Fischer: ONE THING I WANT TO
SAY, THE REAL HEROES OUT OF THIS
STUFF ARE DEAD.
>> Paukner: THANK YOU.
ABSOLUTELY.
>> Familglietti: ABSOLUTELY.
>> Fischer: THEY'RE NOT HERE.
NOBODY HERE IS... IS A HERO.
WE JUST DID WHAT EVERYBODY ELSE
DID.
THE... THE TRUE HEROES ARE
PEOPLE WHO WENT INTO THOSE
BUILDINGS AND THEY NEVER MADE IT
OUT.
>> GO TO 60minutesovertime.com
TO WATCH DR. LUFT'S
EXTRAORDINARY INTERVIEWS WITH
>> Pelley: I'M SCOTT PELLEY.
WE'LL BE BACK NEXT WEEK WITH
ANOTHER EDITION OF "60 MINUTES."
JUST AHEAD ON CBS, ROBERT
De NIRO HOSTS "9/11: TEN YEARS
LATER," AN UPDATE OF THE AWARD-
WINNING FILM WHICH, WITH THE
ONLY CAMERAS INSIDE THE WORLD
TRADE CENTER DURING THE ATTACKS,
REMAINS ONE OF THE MOST
IMPORTANT HISTORIC RECORDS OF
THE TRAGEDY AND THE HEROISM OF
THAT DAY.